Guide to the French transvestite postcards, circa 1900-1930.
French transvestite postcards
- Series I. Music Hall and Theater Postcards
  - Jeanne Bloch, dans Armand’ retour de Londres. En Sca...là, j’marche, revue, circa 1910; 96 (Folder 11)
    Notes: Comic actor and singer Jeanne Bloch (1858–1916) dressed as a portly, bearded man wearing a top hat and carrying a cane. The word “Scala” appears at upper left on the recto, indicating that Bloch was appearing at La Scala, a music hall in Paris open from 1874 to 1936. Divided verso, indicating that the card was produced after 1903. Light spotting to recto.
  - Odéon. Clara Faurens, Postmarked 1905; 97 (Folder 11)
    Performer: Clara Faurens
    Photographer: M.J.S.
    Inscription: On recto: “Emilienne” On verso: Brief note to Jeanne Gorno signed E. Hacquet
    Notes: Stage and silent-film actor Clara Faurens appearing at the Théatre de l’Odéon (Paris) in the role of Pierrot, the commedia dell’arte stock figure of the lovesick clown. Divided verso. Crease to outside lower corner; wear to right margin of recto; stamp and postmark on recto.
- Music and Operetta
  - Chavarny, "Postmarked 1904"; 98 (Folder 11)
    Performer: Chavarny
    Photographer: Gricelly
    Printer/Publisher: D.P
    Inscription: "Addressed to Isabelle Garon; signature of sender illegible."
    Notes: "Performer dressed as an 18th-century male aristocrat in a beribboned outfit and an enormous feathered cavalier hat. The word “Scala” appears at upper left on the photo, indicating that Mlle. Chavarny appeared at La Scala, a music hall in the 10th arrondissement of Paris open from 1874 to 1936 where many of the grand stars of the era appeared."
  - Declos Gaity, "Postmarked 1903"; 99 (Folder 11)
    Performer: Declos and Gaity
    Printer/Publisher: "AS with fleur-de-lys graphic between letters"
    Inscription: "Addressed to Clara (?) Boissier. Brief message with illegible signature on recto."
    Notes: "Two female performers flirting in a coupled dance pose, one dressed as woman in folkloric springtime mountaingirl garb, the other dressed as a young man in a tasseled cap, doublet, short pants and hose. The word “Cigale” appears at upper right on the recto, indicating that Mlle. Declos and Mlle. Gaity appeared at La Cigale, a music hall on the Place Pigalle in Paris that opened in 1887. Postage stamp and postmark on verso."
  - Defrance, "Postmarked 1904"; 100 (Folder 11)
    Performer: Defrance
    Printer/Publisher: D.P.
    Notes: "Performer dressed as an 18th-century male aristocrat in a lacy outfit and cavalier hat and carrying a sword. The word “Scala” appears at upper left on the photo, indicating that Mlle. Defrance appeared at La Scala, a music hall in the 10th arrondissement of Paris open from 1874 to 1936 where many of the grand stars of the era appeared."
  - "Théâtre de Variétés. Barbe Bleue.", "Postmarked 1900"; 101 (Folder 11)
    Performer: Mlle Noray
    Photographer: Paul Boyer
    Printer/Publisher: S.I.P.
    Inscription: "Addressed to Rose Bounias; brief message on recto signed P. Paul"
    Notes: "Actress dressed as a 17th-century cavalier, likely in the role of one of the brothers in a production of Jacques Offenbach’s opéra-bouffe Barbe-Bleue (1866)."
  - Liseron, circa 1915.; 102 (Folder 11)
    Performer: Liseron.
    Photographer: Parisiana
    Medium: Hand-tinted black and white (collotype).
    Notes: Minor wear to margins. A particularly young and boyish performer; this postcard is scarce — I have seen no other examples.
- Series II. Gallant Scenes of a Cross-dressed Woman Wooing another Woman
  - Les Soeurs Mante de l'Opéra, circa 1907; 39 (Folder 5)
    Performer: Suzanne & Blanche Mante
    Photographer: [B]oyer
    Notes: Suzanne and Blanche Mante, lead dancers for the Opéra de Paris, enact a variation of an 18th-century galant scene with one dressed as a woman swooning onto the chest of the other dressed as a man. Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto. Se renseigner à la poste”. Printed on verso: Two five-point stars followed by Série No 958. Hand-coloring includes gold highlights.
  - La Matchiche, Postmarked 1908; 40, 41 (Folder 5)
    Performer: Fanny & Alice de Tender
    Photographer: Stebbing
    Printer/Publisher: F.K. [probably Frères Kunzli]
    Medium: RPT
    Notes: Set of two postcards portraying the De Tender sisters, both music-hall performers. Alice de Tender appeared at the Folies-Bergère, the Eldorado and the Moulin Rouge; she also appeared in silent films, including the feature La Veuve Joyeuse (1913) and a number of shorts. "La Matchiche"was a popular song debuted in a music-hall show in 1902; the painter Kees van Dongen borrowed the title for a 1904 oil representing dancers at the bal populaire Le Moulin de la Galette (collection of the Musée d'Art Moderne de Troyes). Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto (Se renseigner à la poste)"Series number indicated on recto: 405.
  - Estudiantina, circa 1907; 42-44 (Folder 5)
    Notes: Series of three postcards. The title may refer to a waltz made popular by an 1883 arrangement by Emile Waldteufel. Further research might therefore identify these images as relating to a theatrical production. Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto. Se renseigner à la Poste”. Printed on verso: One five-point star followed by Série N. 785. Hand-coloring includes gold highlights.
  - Amours Champêtres, circa 1907; 45 (Folder 5)
    Photographer: Waléry
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto. Se renseigner à la Poste”. Printed on verso: Two five-point stars followed by Série N. 663. Hand-coloring includes gold highlights.
  - On ne passe pas, Postmarked 1903; 46 (Folder 5)
    Printer/Publisher: Kunzli Frères Editeurs
    Notes: Undivided verso
  - Je suis épris de toi, Postmarked 1907; 47 (Folder 5)
  - Les Cerises, circa 1900; 48-57 (Folder 6)
    Printer/Publisher: K.F. Editeurs (Kunzli Frères)
    Notes: Set of 10 cards with photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene. "Male"climbs ladder to pick cherries, offers to female, tries to kiss her. Undivided verso (address only).
  - Ma belle Marquise, circa 1910; 58, 59 (Folder 6)
    Printer/Publisher: Monogram SIP in a circle.
    Notes: Set of 2 cards with photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene. "Male"aristocrat woos and kisses a marquise in a studio-set salon. Divided verso; stamp and postmark on recto. Series no. 1549.
  - [Untitled], circa 1900; 60-63 (Folder 7)
    Printer/Publisher: Monogram ABN inside a half-sunburst.
    Notes: Set of 4 cards with photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene. "Male"aristocrat woos a female aristocrat in a studio-set salon. No imprinted captions. Divided verso. Series no. 525.
  - Idylle à Trianon, postmarked 1902; 64-66 (Folder 7)
    Photographer: H. Manuel
    Inscription: Dated 2/6/03 in purple ink on lower margin
    Notes: Set of 3 cards with photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene. "Male"officer invites a female aristocrat to dance in a studio-set salon. Numbered VII, VIII and XI; each card has two to three lines of dialogue on the verso. Undivided verso. Small green glue spot on verso of each card (recto unaffected).
  - Amourette Louis XV, circa 1900; 67, 68 (Folder 7)
    Notes: Set of 2 cards with photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene. "Male"aristocrat woos a female aristocrat in a studio-set formal garden. Blank verso with manuscript address; stamp and postmark on corner of recto.
  - [Fanluchette et Godichon], 1904; 69-78 (Folder 8)
    Printer/Publisher: [Piprot]
    Notes: Full set of 10 cards with photo narrative of an early 19th-century seduction scene. "Male"soldier wearing a shako declares his love to a country girl in a studio setting with a backdrop painting of a forest clearing. Postcards numbered 1–10, each with a one- to two-sentence narrative. Mounted in a trifold cardstock holder imprinted with an art nouveau foliage pattern (cards remo­va­ble—held in corner slots). Undivided verso. Listed in "Bibliographie de la France: Gravures, Lithogra­phies, Photographies,"Journal général de l'imprimerie et de la librairie, vol. 93 (1904): page 13.
  - [Aristocrat and Flower Girl], Dated 1911; 103 (Folder 12)
    Printer/Publisher: "Edit. d’Art PH Card No. 101"
    Inscription: "Long personal message addressed to “Mon cher enfant” and signed L. Génirmont."
    Impersonator: Gallant Scene (cross-dressed woman wooing another woman)
    Notes: "Eighteenth-century seduction scene: woman dressed as a male aristocrat woos a peasant-girl flower-seller against a studio backdrop of a sylvan scene. Postage stamp and postmark on recto. Divided verso."
  - [Violinist], circa 1900; 104 (Folder 12)
    Inscription: "Addressed to Mlle Fanny Grollier. Brief note at lower margin of recto signed Melanie B."
    Notes: "Young woman dressed in 18th-century men’s garb playing a violin against a studio backdrop of a bower.’"
  - 1er Avril, Postmarked 1905; 105-106 (Folder 12)
    Printer/Publisher: A & Cie
    Inscription: "Addressed to two different recipients"
    Medium: "Black-and-White Real Photo Hand-Tinted Real Photo"
    Notes: "Series of 2 April Fool’s Day (“poisson d’avril”) postcards. Two women dressed in 18th-century aristocratic garb, one as a man, one as woman: In one card (untinted), both hold a basket filled with flowers and fish. Divided verso. Stamp and postmark on verso. In the other (tinted), each is holding a colossal fish (montaged into the negative). Undivided verso. Stamp and postmark on verso. Brief personal message and date handwritten on side margins of recto. A doggerel verse printed on the recto of each refers to the pair in the photo as “ces marquis gracieux.”"
  - Chassé-croisé, circa 1900; 107-111 (Folder 12)
    Printer/Publisher: "PA Logo resembling a petasus (winged hat) Series No. R.P.I. 156"
    Inscription: "Addressed to Mesdemoiselles Bonnet; signed on recto of each card: Henriette."
    Notes: "Series of 5 postcards number I through V showing an 18thcentury picnic with two women being courted by two men: One of the men is a woman cross-dressed as an officer; the other is a man dressed as a man. The scenes take place on a set with a rustic fence and a faux stream with a studio backdrop of a wooded dell. The series is highly unusual as the only postcards of the genre documented to date that represent a cross-dressed woman and a man dressed as a man both portraying male roles. Undivided verso. One card bears a readable postmark making it possible to date the mailing to 1905. Stamp primarily on verso, but with approximately 1 cm folded over onto upper margin of recto."
  - Le Droit de passage, "Postmarked 1903"; 112-117 (Folder 13)
    Printer/Publisher: "F.K. éd. [Frères Kunzli]"
    Inscription: "Series of love notes addressed to a woman named Albertine Frémoul from a man identifying himself as “votre fiancé” (signature partially illegible: “G. Rammeno...”"
    Notes: "Set of 5 cards with photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene. “Male” aristocrat woos a female country girl encountered on a footbridge. The captions recount the tale: “Le Droit de passage,” “L’Invitation,” “Le Beau raisin,” “Le Goûter,” “La Déclaration.” Postage stamp and postmark on recto of each card. Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating “Carte Postale. Tous le pays étrangers n’acceptent pas la correspondence au recto (se renseigner à la poste) Also included: Variant edition of “L’Invitation” postmarked 1900; brighter printing makes photo details more visible; differing hand-tinting; undivided verso; brief manuscript message on recto."
  - Idylle à Trianon, "postmarked 1902"; 118-120 (Folder 13)
    Inscription: "Brief handwritten note on upper margin of recto on each card; dated 1902."
    Notes: "Set of 3 cards with photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene. “Male” officer invites a female aristocrat to dance in a studio-set salon. Numbered I, II and X (missing from the postcards in this series already held by Cornell). Undivided verso. Address, stamp and postmarks on verso."
  - Il m’aime..., "Postmarked 1905"; 121-123 (Folder 13)
    Printer/Publisher: "F.K. [Frères Kunzli]"
    Inscription: Address
    Notes: "Series of 3 postcards of a woman dressed in late 18th-century officer’s wear including a tricorn hat reacting to declarations from a woman in a gauzy dress and flowered hat. The woman is reciting the traditional French equivalent of “he loves me, he loves me not” while plucking petals from a flower. Cards numbered I, II and III. Each postcard after the first has a rhyming couplet as a caption on the recto. The first two refrains are offered here (“un peu” and “beaucoup”); the series presumably had three more cards for the refrains missing here (“passionément,” “à la folie” and “pas de tout”). Spotting to all three cards; damp stain to lower half of card no. III."
  - Le Marquis amoureux, "Postmarked 1904"; 124-128 (Folder 14)
    Inscription: "Brief handwritten note on upper right corner of recto on each card: “Tout à toi,” “Bon souvenir,” etc. Addressed to Mlle Berthe Best."
    Notes: "Complete series of 5 postcards showing a woman dressed as an 18th-century marquis courting another woman dressed as a female aristocrat, ending with a scene of the marquis stealing a kiss. Minor spotting. Address, stamp and postmarks on verso."
  - Va, c’est fini, je te déteste., "Postmarked 1906"; 129-134 (Folder 14)
    Inscription: "All the cards are addressed to Angèle Lobet in Reims; most are signed by Blanche or “Bl. Lobet,” but one with a brief message in a shaky hand with a spelling correction is signed Pierre Daigremeont."
    Medium: Hand-Tinted Black-and-White Printing (collotype)
    Notes: "Complete series of 6 postcards showing a young woman dressed as an 18th-century shepherd having a lover’s spat with a young woman dressed as a shepherdess. The scene takes place on a fake lawn in front of a studio backdrop of low hills and a lake. Each postcard has one line of a six-line verse offering the dialogue of the lovers. Divided verso. Stamp and postmark on recto; postmark on verso. Minor damp stain to outside upper corner of two cards."
  - [Aristocrat Courting], "Postmarked 1902"; 135-139 (Folder 15)
    Printer/Publisher: "Possible publisher’s logo: White star at lower left corner of each photo"
    Inscription: "Brief manuscript message providing a caption in the lower margin of the recto of each postcard (“Ah! Attention!!!!!!”; “Ça s’embrouille”; etc.). Each message is signed “Jane.”"
    Notes: "Complete series of five postcards showing a woman dressed as an 18th-century male aristocrat wearing an epée who pays court to a woman in a flowered dress and with flowers in her hair. In the final scene, the man helps the woman wind a ball of yarn, suggesting romantic entanglement (and possible future domesticity). All the scenes are set against a blank studio backdrop. Postage stamp and postmark (but no mailing address) on the verso of each card. Photo: Cartes03"
  - [Egg], "Postmarked 1903"; 140-145 (Folder 15)
    Inscription: "Addressed to Mademoiselle A. Lefort; signed on recto of each card: five signed G.M.; one signed Germaine. Brief message on lower right corner of recto of each card, two in English, the rest in French. Message on lastmailed card indicates “Merci, c’est la dernière.”"
    Notes: "Complete series of six postcards showing an enormous egg in front of a painted backdrop of a bucolic landscape. Over the series, the egg opens into left and right halves to reveal a woman dressed as an 18th-century male aristocrat who pays court to a woman dressed as a female aristocrat. The couple remains ensconced in the egg, using it as a place to sit once its fully open. Postmarks show the cards were mailed successively during the course of two months, with a message on the final one in the photo-narrative stating, “Thanks, this is the last one.” The dates and inscription suggest how such series were sometimes used to sustain interest in a friendly correspondence over time. Postage stamp and postmark on one corner on verso of each card. Curved impression to corners of cards indicating the set was once place in a die-cut postcard holder. Photo: Cartes01"
  - Amourette Louis XV, Dated 1907; 146-150 (Folder 15)
    Inscription: "Addressed to Charles Ventre (greeted as “Mon joli” or “mon petit”). Brief message on recto of all cards signed “ta Jeanette.” Three cards have longer love notes on the verso (printed with an undivided address panel, but with a hand-drawn vertical line to produce a message panel)."
    Notes: "Set of five postcards with a photo narrative of an 18th-century seduction scene involving a marquis and marquise: A woman dressed as a male aristocrat woos a female aristocrat in a studio-set formal garden. Each card includes a brief caption on near lower margin of the recto with a line of dialog. The first scene shows the female aristocrat seated by herself reading a book; the male aristocrat arrives and ultimately persuades her in the final scene: “Mettons en action le roman!” Undivided verso headed “Union Postale Universelle / Carte Postale” (with “postcard” also indicated in six other languages). The series thus dates to earlier than 1903, when postal regulations where changed to permit both a message and an address on the verso of postcards. Postage stamp folded from recto to verso on all cards; postmark on recto of four cards and verso of one card; minor creasing to upper margin of two cards."
  - "Amoureux Viennois: Le Baiser", "Postmarked 1905"; 151 (Folder 15)
    Printer/Publisher: Royer
    Notes: "One postcard (no. 3) from a series of unknown length representing a woman dressed as a male officer in a braided uniform adapted for added raciness (tailored for maximum form fitting, sleeves removed to bare the arms). The officer kisses the hand of a seated woman wearing a braided dress designed to echo the uniform. The two wear matching boots. Corners somewhat worn. Photo: Cartes03"
  - Pierette et Polichinelle, "Postmarked 1904"; 152 (Folder 15)
    Printer/Publisher: "A. Bergeret & Cie."
    Inscription: "Addressed to Monsieur Madam Jouvencon. Brief message on recto from “ta petite famille” signed Justine."
    Notes: "Photo-illustration of two stock characters from Italian commedia dell’arte: The cruel and crafty bachelor Punchinello, played by a cross-dressed woman, whispers into the ear of the pretty ingénue Pierrette, played by a woman dressed as a woman. Although the card refers to a theatrical form, it likely does not relate to a specific production of a play, as it makes no mention of a theater or the names of the performers. Undivided verso, indicating that the card was produced before 1903."
- Series III. Humor and Other
  - Illusions perdues, circa 1920; 79 (Folder 9)
    Medium: Black and white caricature
    Notes: Real photo reproduction of a line-drawing caricature: "Woman"undressing revealed to be a skinny man. Divided verso imprinted "No 14"and "Made in France - Fabriqué en France”
  - La plus sérieuse des Lorientaises, 1917; 80 (Folder 9)
    Photographer: Arnaud et Nozais
    City: Nantes
    Notes: Portly, mustachioed man dressed as a peasant woman carrying a basket and an umbrella.
  - Bergère et berger, Postmarked 1904, 1906; 153-154 (Folder 16)
    Printer/Publisher: MJS
    Impersonator: "Male Impersonator Female Impersonator"
    Notes: "Series of 2 comic postcards of a shepherdess and a shepherd. Both emphasize supposedly outlandish folkloric highlander clothing. One shows a woman dressed as a shepherd; a doggerel verse printed in red on the recto refers to the character as “Lubin,” a man in search of his “chère Annette.” The studio set shows a rustic fence and a sylvan painted backdrop. The other postcard shows Lubin holding an umbrella over a seated shepherdess, played by a man wearing an absurdly obvious wig, outsized flowered hat and simple peasant frock; a toylike stuffed sheep is visible at right. This card has a handwritten message on the verso: “Deux fiancées.” Considerable wear, creasing and scattered spotting to both cards."
  - Bonne Année, Dated 1930; 155 (Folder 16)
    Printer/Publisher: "ABC Card No. 1812"
    Inscription: "Addressed to “Bien chère Gaby” and signed “Mes meilleurs voeux, mes bonnes amitiés—Une petite amie.” Long personal message about health issues, life troubles, hopes to see friend in the coming year."
    Notes: "Studio photo of a garçonne—the French “new young women” of the 1920s who appropriated a variety of masculine privileges: dressing in mannish clothes, smoking in public, playing sports, driving cars and openly pursuing lovers of both sexes, evoking both horror and titillation among conservatives. The style of the garçonne portrayed on this postcard is clearly titled toward a more feminine presentation of the supposedly male signifiers. Divided verso imprinted “Made in France — Fabriqué en France”"
  - Bonne Année, "Postmarked 1907"; 156 (Folder 16)
    Printer/Publisher: "JO No. 179"
    Inscription: "New year’s greetings to “Ma chère Henriette” at Castle Hall School in Northampton, England; signed “Ton amie qui t’embrasse, Jeanne Lambert”"
    Notes: "Slim young woman dressed as a mailman in front of a studio backdrop of a village gate. Divided verso. Also included: Variant edition with differing tinting; publisher given as E.N., card number as 8179; art nouveau graphic divider on verso; postmarked 1905. Personal message addressed to “Chère amie” (Félice Pinty) signed Marguerite."
  - Bonne Année, Dated 1913; 157 (Folder 16)
    Inscription: "E.N. Card No. 8179"
    Notes: "Slim young woman dressed as a mailman in front of a studio backdrop of a village gate. Same model, costume and set as preceding card, but differing pose. Holding mail. Divided verso."
  - Bonne Année, Postmarked 1909; 158 (Folder 16)
    Notes: "Slim young woman dressed as a mailman in front of a studio backdrop of a village gate. Same model, costume and set as preceding card, but differing pose. Holding flowers. Divided verso."
  - Bonne et heureuse année, Dated 1909; 159 (Folder 16)
    Inscription: "DOL Card No. 196"
    Notes: "Slim young woman dressed as a mailman seen through a painted frame illustrating letters and a mail-carrying case. Recto inscribed in black ink: “1er Janvier 1909 / Georgette”. Divided verso."
  - Cléodinerie, "Postmarked 1903"; 160 (Folder 16)
    Inscription: "A. Bergeret et Ce"
    Notes: "Skinny, homely man wearing a wig, pearls and a flowered tutu posing as a ballerina with arms in fifth position. The card is a spoof of the celebrated dancer and demimondaine Cléo de Mérode (1875–1966). A doggerel verse printed in red on the recto refers to the dancer’s charms as designed to “captiver un prince.” Addressed, stamped and postmarked on verso."
  - Mademoiselle, écoutez-moi donc, circa 1910; 161-166 (Folder 16)
    Notes: "Complete series of 6 postcards showing a woman dressed as a sporty young man approaching a properly dressed young woman in the street and convincing her to learn how to ride the young man’s bicycle. The narrative takes place in front of a painted studio backdrop of a Paris city scene: a wine shop at right, a kiosk at left in the middle distance, and the Panthéon in the background. Each card includes a snippet of dialog between the two characters; the woman identifies herself in one as an “ouvrière dans une grande maison de Modes de la Rue de la Paix.” Divided verso; imprinted “a utiliser seulement dans le régime intérieur (FRANCE, ALGERIE et TUNISIE).”"